Empresses in the Palace—the Legend of Zhen Huan
Adapted from the novel by Liu Lian Zi
Translators: The Magpie Bridge Brigade 鹊桥小队翻译组
https://magpiebridgebrigade.cn
Twitter/FB/IG @BrigadeMagpie 公众号/微博: 鹊桥小队翻译组
Theme: Unfortunate Love
Perturbed by the thoughts on my mind
no matter how hard I try to sever my love.
I could give away my crown for the beauty by my side,
but the wheel of fortune turns weals into woes,
and woes into weals.
No one is the master of their own destiny,
the vicissitudes throughout their life.
For the lovers of all time,
who can break the spell of romance?
I could give away my crown for the beauty by my side,
but the wheel of fortune turns weals into woes,
and woes into weals.
No one is the master of their own destiny,
the vicissitudes throughout their life.
For the lovers of all time,
who can break the spell of romance?
Who can break the spell of romance?
Translators: The Magpie Bridge Brigade 鹊桥小队翻译组
https://magpiebridgebrigade.cn
Twitter/FB/IG @BrigadeMagpie 公众号/微博: 鹊桥小队翻译组
The weather is getting cold.
The Household Department will send over
winter supplies in a couple of days.
Tell Chief Jiang that
we want to exchange all our scheduled
clothes and material for charcoal and a brazier.
Yes.
Also, ask him to send more narcissus and plum blossoms.
I'm glad that Jiang Zhongmin is
grateful and knows to repay your favor.
He has been sending all we requested
as long as it is within his capabilities.
You must supply plenty of charcoal to the Warm Chamber,
and personally bring fresh flowers here
three times a day to feed the butterflies.
Yes.
Remember to do it yourself.
I will.
Is my dress ready?
Yes, it is.
Go get it.
The cloak is made of fine satin with the pattern of
clouds and swan geese, per your bidding My Lady.
Here, and the color is "connected sky and waters".
Yes, this is just what I want.
You've finally made up your mind to dress nicely.
I have dressed plainly for the past months
not only because there was no worthy person to adorn myself for
but also honoring my child in the mourning period.
Have you gotten over it?
Thanks for enlightening me, Meizhuang.
I am no longer who I was.
Good.
We should act quickly, now that you have the intention.
Your Majesty,
I was impetuous in carrying out my duty
and lost propriety.
I entreat
Your Majesty's forgiveness
by virtue of our years of affection
Song Zhi, when I finish, send this letter to Su Peisheng
and ask him to deliver it to His Majesty.
Your Highness has suffered such indignity for His Majesty's sake.
Whether it's indignity
or pleading for understanding,
I simply wish that His Majesty would cease ignoring me
and remember the old times.
I heard that the Palace of Pearl Jade is in the same situation.
His Majesty never summoned Concubine Sourire again.
She deserves it.
I don't care about her now.
All I want is His Majesty to have me in his heart.
Not soft enough. Stew it for longer.
You fan too forcefully.
Stew with gentle heat.
The black chicken doesn't taste good if it's hardened.
Watch the stove.
Put in some dried dates and astragalus later.
My Lady looks pale. She needs those nourishing herbs.
- Jade, can you lend me a hand?
- Aye.
Can you move the butterflies a bit forward?
Ahh, it smells so good.
Good heavens, how can it not be?
I have to bring out the fragrance to perfume My Lady's cloak.
You'll have to watch the fire closely
in order to keep the butterflies warm.
Your Majesty.
Why did Your Majesty sigh?
I am reading a pleading letter from Nian.
Every word is sincere.
It makes me think about the past years with her.
"Each day in a marriage fosters a hundred days of devotion."
Your Majesty is a person with lasting affection.
It's reasonable to feel emotional about the past.
It has been so long, Sourire's sorrow over her loss should have lightened.
If Your Majesty misses Consort Nian,
you should visit Her Highness.
I don't have the heart to visit Concubine Sourire,
let alone Consort Nian.
Forget it.
I disdain those who "adorn themselves to please others".
But now,
I can only please him with my appearance.
I heard that Consort Nian submitted a sincere
pleading letter to seek punishment from His Majesty.
His Majesty was touched, but hasn't made any comments.
Nian Gengyao is "burningly favored" in the imperial court.
Given that, Nian Shilan will eventually regain favor.
That would put "thorns and thistles in our hands".
Look, it's snowing.
Yes.
On the day of the first snowfall,
His Majesty always hosts a family banquet
at the Palace of Commencing Celebration.
The first snowfall came later than usual.
It did, but it is a heavy one.
"Timely snow foretells a bumper harvest."
Next year will enjoy peace and prosperity.
Is Concubine Sourire still not attending?
She sent Jinxi over early this morning
to report that she was feeling unwell.
So I permitted her to rest for a few days.
No wonder the banquet looks emptier.
Noble Lady Cao stayed in her palace because
Princess Wenyi is sensitive to the cold.
Your Majesty, Noble Lady Vertu also hasn't arrived.
She is always punctual.
Why is she late today ?
Perhaps she was delayed walking in the snow.
Peace to Your Majesties.
I was delayed on my way here.
I hope Your Majesties will pardon me.
It's all right. You may rise.
I thank Your Majesty.
What caused your delay today?
Was there something wrong?
I saw the newly blooming plum trees
when I passed the Garden of Leaning Plums.
I was captivated and lost track of time.
Have the plum trees all come into bloom?
They are beautifully in full bloom.
Lady Vertu, such a beautiful view must not go unappreciated.
Would you walk with me to the garden?
I'm honored, Your Majesty.
Plum blossoms afire in the winter snow.
Your Majesty must not keep this
pleasurable scene to yourself.
Please also bring us along.
His Majesty departs for the Garden of Leaning Plums.
My Lady, Lady Vertu is bringing His Majesty here.
Dear Buddha, your pious disciple from the
Zhen family lacks the virtue
to carry an imperial heir.
I am not worthy to be seen by His Majesty.
I am praying here for my Emperor to receive blessings from Heaven.
May peace and joy abide in His Majesty
for ten thousand years and more.
If my wish is fulfilled, I will practice vegetarianism all my life
and abstain from physical service to His Majesty.
Huan Huan ...
Is that you?
I am a virtueless concubine.
I don't deserve to greet Your Majesty.
Why don't you look at me?
Do you no longer want to see me?
Your Majesty, don't ...
My shoes and socks are wet.
That was what you said in the garden that year.
You Majesty still remembers.
But I don't dare to recall it anymore.
Your hands are so cold.
Have you no fear of falling ill again?
I was thinking only about praying for Your Majesty.
It will be my fault if I make Your Majesty worry about me.
Please allow me to take my leave.
Look, Concubine Sourire is surrounded by so many butterflies.
This is witchcraft!
How could there be butterflies in the winter?
The butterflies are also drawn to you.
I wasn't aware.
If you get sick from praying for me in the snow,
that will just keep breaking my heart.
You infuse the air with fragrance.
It is no surprise that the butterflies
were drawn to you on a winter day.
I am just the same — my heart inebriated.
I have been praying day and night for Your Majesty.
Bathing and burning incense,
mindful of every slight detail.
This is wonderful.
Concubine Sourire has not set foot
out of her chamber since her miscarriage.
I have been worried for several months.
I have prayed for Your Majesty and Sourire day and night,
hoping you both would be reconciled from your rift.
Today, it has come true.
Was there ever a rift between Huan Huan and myself?
Never.
I was unwell and could not serve Your Majesty.
Are you happy now?
Happy for our masters.
As their servant,
we are happy only when our masters are pleased.
I never spared my praises of
Concubine Sourire before His Majesty.
Did you?
You make every effort to please His Majesty, always.
And today was Lady Vertu’s effort.
This is strange.
Lady Vertu would rather help Concubine Sourire than herself.
Even though her favor now is not comparable to before she was fully recovered.
True.
Stay outside, all of you.
I resent mentioning it but we gave her so much trouble the other day -
punishing her with kneeling.
And then you humiliated her intensely.
Guess what?
She regained favor simply by "twisting her wrist".
Didn’t you see today
how His Majesty ignored everyone else after seeing her?
Are there going to be any good days for us?
What is Your Highness worrying about?
Every woman in the palace gains favor and loses it.
She is a Concubine.
I am a Noble Lady.
Your Highness is a Consort.
We are two against one.
What's there to be worried about?
Two against one, you say?
Is the fight for favor a game about numbers?
I doubt Concubine Sourire will let us off easily.
But Your Highness still holds the rank of Consort.
It's perfectly reasonable for you to discipline the concubines.
Besides, there is no evidence about the oleander incident.
There's nothing Concubine Sourire can do against us.
Who knows?
Let it be.
My Lady, you must be tired from today.
Will you go to bed now?
I do feel a bit tired, but I don't want to sleep yet.
Why did they make the charcoal so much warmer today?
They used the same amount of charcoal.
However, your state of mind has changed, My Lady.
That's why the charcoal feels warmer to you than usual.
I used to think that the actions and words of
His Majesty mattered more than anything else.
But now that I think of it,
they are not as reliable as this tub of charcoal.
I once wished for "The love of a whole heart,
until gray-haired we would never part".
Looking back, it was a foolish wish.
Nevertheless,
His Majesty puts you above everyone else at the moment.
That is exactly why
this feels like "the flower in the mirror"
and "the moon in the water".
His Majesty can treat me like this,
and he can treat anyone else just the same.
There is nothing I can do
except to act with cleverness
to gain what I want.
My Lady, you have been suppressing your feelings in your recovery.
Now that you have spoken them out,
they will no longer be a burden on you.
My Lady, our palace gates will be locked soon.
We should go to bed now.
I'm afraid it won't be a peaceful night for sleeping.
My Lady, His Majesty is here.
Don't invite His Majesty in.
Inform His Majesty that I've already gone to sleep.
Yes.
Translators: The Magpie Bridge Brigade 鹊桥小队翻译组
Twitter/FB/IG @BrigadeMagpie 公众号/微博: 鹊桥小队翻译组
Who is it?
Huan Huan, have you gone to bed?
What brings Your Majesty here so late?
I'm already in bed.
Huan Huan, are you feeling better?
My mind will not be at ease until I have checked on you.
Your Majesty, I have not recovered from my cold.
I'm not able to attend Your Majesty
and I hope Your Majesty can understand.
Huan Huan,
I just want to come in and have one look at you.
Just one look.
I just want to see you are well.
Your Majesty needs to attend court early in the morning.
Your Majesty should not stay up late.
I'm already in bed.
Getting up will prolong my recovery
and that will further delay my service to Your Majesty.
I hope Your Majesty will accommodate my request.
I'll return in that case.
- Xiao-Yunzi
- Yes
- See His Majesty out.
- Yes.
I bid Your Majesty goodbye.
Bring me some water to wash up.
Now I can sleep in peace.
My Lady, it's snowing quite heavily outside.
Why didn't you let His Majesty in to see you?
I also won't see His Majesty if he comes tomorrow.
Your Majesty, it's very late now.
Which palace would you like to stay in?
I don't think Lady An has slept yet.
Or the Empress or Lady Vertu ...
No.
Head back to the Hall of Mental Cultivation.
Yes.
I'll go to ...
The Hall of Converging Light.
Yes.
To the Hall of Converging Light.
Your Majesty asked me to stay the night
saying I drank too much.
But it seems like it was because you need to
have tea with someone in case you couldn't sleep.
Don't mention it.
I wasn't welcomed wherever I went.
But Your Majesty has a harem of so many palaces.
I do. I have so many palaces.
But I only wanted to go to the Palace of Pearl Jade.
Yet I was pushed away by one excuse after another.
Concubine Sourire said she was ill and unable to serve me.
She wouldn't even let me take a look at her.
Concubine Sourire was not wrong, though.
She was caring for you.
I know that she was, but ...
Looks like Her Highness's butterflies
flew into Your Majesty's heart.
I have no idea where those butterflies came from.
Regardless, it is more important
that she has given her heart to me.
You have no idea how stubborn Concubine Sourire is.
Because I was unwilling to impose
severe punishment on Consort Nian,
she avoided seeing me for months.
What an small-minded woman!
But this small-minded woman touches the heart.
Who says these unmarried lords know nothing about marriage?
I've been following Your Majesty for years.
But besides Empress Première,
I haven't heard Your Majesty talk about anyone else like this.
Although state affairs are like tangled threads,
I can sort them out from thousands of strings.
But once a smart woman focuses on trivial matters,
that is more trouble than the state affairs.
That's why I adore simple and dutiful women.
But that kind of adorable doesn't mean you will love them.
Sounds like I'm having tea with the right person.
If Your Majesty is fond of Concubine Sourire,
Your Majesty should take your time.
A knot in one's heart can't be untied within a day or two.
Since Concubine Sourire hasn't untied hers,
Your Majesty should accommodate her.
Su Peisheng!
Your Majesty, you are still awake?
Hasn't the dawn broken yet?
It's the middle of the night.
About four hours until dawn.
I'm going to sleep.
Extinguish two more candles.
Yes, Your Majesty.
His Majesty the Emperor.
Peace to Your Majesty.
All rise.
I thank Your Majesty.
Your Majesty just finished court.
Is there anything bothering Your Majesty?
I need to discuss one thing with the Empress.
Since you are all here, you may as well hear it.
Today at the court, Dzungar Khanate [Region] sent
an envoy to seek a marriage alliance.
Their Yingge Khagan asks to marry
a princess of the Great Qing Empire
in order to placate the people in the border area.
Our imperial princesses commonly
marry down to a neighboring state.
We can select a suitable lady from the imperial clan
and grant her the title of Noble Princess.
This time is difficult because
they request to marry a princess of the emperor
not a princess from the imperial clan.
Dzungar Khanate is a tributory state of the Qing Empire
and a mere tribe on the borderlands.
It's their great honor to have a princess from the Great Qing.
How can they be so demanding —
asking for a princess of an emperor?
When we give them a inch, they want a yard.
Marriage alliance usually occurs in the imperial clan.
I remember that the prior emperor allowed
the marriage of his daughter Princess Lanqi to the Dzungar Khagan.
Yes, because of this precedent,
I can't easily reject their request.
Your Majesty, Wenyi is your daughter,
but she is a child... too young for a marriage alliance!
Had Wenyi come of age,
I wouldn't be troubled so much.
You are all aware of the tension in court.
It is less than three years since my coronation,
and we've just pacified the Northwest.
Dzungar Khanate has always been aggressive.
I'm afraid if they are not satisfied with the settlement,
a war would be started.
And if troops are to be deployed once again,
we might not have sufficient money and supplies.
It's really not the best strategy.
Your Majesty is absolutely right.
State affairs should take the highest priority.
"A country's internal stability flows from pacifying external enemies."
Marriage alliance is the only strategy at the moment.
But my own daughter Princess Wenyi is too young
and there's no other suitable person.
They only asked for "a princess of an emperor".
So it doesn't have to be Your Majesty's daughter.
You mean ...
Princess Zhaogui, youngest daughter of the previous emperor,
is still young and her marriage has not been arranged.
She would be the most appropriate candidate.
But ...
She is my youngest sister.
Your Majesty has already devoted
yourself to the country day and night.
Your Majesty should not withhold
a sister by a different mother.
Besides, Princess Zhaogui's mother was
just a Noble Lady of the prior emperor.
Even though Your Majesty will assign a
marriage to her in the years to come,
it would be to an undistinguished family from the court.
How can that compare to a
dignified marriage to a Dzungar Khagan?
You're right.
She is my only unmarried sister.
I have to make plans for her.
Now that I think of it,
marrying the Dzungar Khagan may be her best choice.
Since Zhaogui is the only candidate,
then the Empress will prepare for her
to marry down to Dzungar Khanate ten days from now.
I'll endeavor to get everything ready for the princess.
For the marriage alliance,
since Zhaogui is already a Noble Princess,
she will be promoted to State Princess.
And her wedding will observe the protocol of State Princess.
Yes.
Preparing the dowry can be an easy task
when supervised by the Household Department.
But it can also be difficult —
not a single mistake can be tolerated.
Otherwise, it would damage the prestige of the imperial family.
The Household Department already
undertakes the tasks for so many people.
I was thinking that
Lady Cao is the most attentive person.
Why don't we seek her help in preparing the princess's dowry?
Your Majesty, I have no experience with this.
I'm afraid I cannot fulfill Your Majesty and Sourire's expectations.
You are a meticulous person.
I believe you're capable of it.
Other things will be decided by the Empress.
Yes.
I have to leave now.
I still have some work in court.
I bid Your Majesty goodbye.
You were quiet for a long time.
But in the end, you proposed that Lady Cao should
prepare the dowry for the marriage alliance.
What were you thinking?
I was quiet because I disagree with this marriage.
But I knew that it was determined.
And I felt sorry for Princess Zhaogui.
Yes, Dzungar is a tribe in the borderland.
Distance doesn't matter if she can marry the person she deserves.
But Yingge Khagan is very old.
He's already in his sixties.
I'm sorry that the princess is in her prime age
and must marry a Khagan who is old enough to be her grandfather!
But His Majesty made it obvious that this marriage has to happen.
"When sending a consort can stabilize the state,
what will be the mission of the generals?"
Isn't Nian Gengyao the most valiant general?
Why doesn't His Majesty send him to quell the borderland?
If it can be pacified by a woman,
why bother sending thousands of soldiers?
Besides, Nian Gengyao has executed extraordinary military feats.
If he loses,
we will lose more than a princess.
If he wins,
Nian Gengyao's unrivaled power will be a menace to his master.
Therefore, marriage alliance is His Majesty's inevitable decision.
His Majesty was sitting here for quite a while
but did he ever look towards you?
I'm incompetent. I could not gain
His Majesty's favorable attention.
It's not that you are incompetent
but Concubine Sourire is too competent.
Without her, you were exclusively in favor.
But when she's around, you cannot even stand level with her.
Sourire hasn't been in favor for a long time.
To His Majesty she must be fresh and new again.
Then what about the future?
It's been quite some time since you gained His Majesty's favor.
Do you still want His Majesty's direct attention?
I seek Your Majesty's advice.
Concubine Sourire was able to advance her
title even before serving His Majesty.
Do you remember the promotion of Noble Lady Chun?
Being close with Concubine Sourire and the
rest of harem will go a long way.
Understood, Your Highness.
You have only one liberty left here.
I lose.
Your Majesty conceded.
Will Your Majesty stay?
You've been asking me to leave every night.
Tonight I finally get to stay?
Since Your Majesty is so fond of the Palace of Pearl Jade,
I have to give it up.
Your Majesty will stay here
and I will stay at Meizhuang's.
Your Majesty said you would stay after losing the game
but you didn't say I had to stay with you.
The night is windy and snowy, and I haven't fully recovered.
If Your Majesty stays, then I will have to leave.
You're still recovering your health. You should stay.
I will go back to the Hall of Mental Cultivation.
I bid Your Majesty goodbye.
My Lady, you have turned His Majesty away for three or four days.
Refusing to allow His Majesty to stay in the Palace of Pearl Jade
has raised so much gossip.
So what about it raising gossip?
They are just saying I'm bewitching His Majesty.
Aren't you afraid, My Lady,
that His Majesty will stop coming?
Have you heard the story about Emperor Wu of Han and Lady Li?
Lady Li was exceedingly beautiful and gained favor from Emperor Wu.
But when Emperor Wu, on his deathbed, wanted to see her,
she veiled her face and refused to reveal it till he died.
Because his love faded as her beauty did
and that is the nightmare of every woman in the harem.
Only what one has lost and what one cannot obtain
are the most precious.
My Lady is "keeping the distance in order to capture the heart".
But eventually, the goal is to "capture".
Distance should only be a means to that end.
Therefore, the timing for the capture is crucial
so that all the past efforts will not be futile.
Poor Princess Zhaogui.
Her wedding is so quiet and lonely.
She didn't even have any visitors.
Her mother holds a humble rank
so His Majesty doesn't have much respect for the princess.
Especially when, after this marriage,
she will never see him again.
How can His Majesty have the heart to do this to his only sister?
Even if it was His Majesty's daughter,
he would have no other options.
Heaven knows which princess will be the next.
Why did Your Majesty not have your arrival announced?
It makes me appear disrespectful to Your Majesty.
I have just seen off Princess Zhaogui's wedding procession.
You were absorbed in your needlework,
so I did not want to interrupt.
I am doing it to pass the time.
How was the Princess?
She cried very sadly.
I couldn't bear to see her like that either.
So I returned as soon as she exited the palace gate.
What are you making?
I was hoping to make a sachet for Your Majesty,
but I've been so slow
that I have only finished embroidering the dragon
and haven't decided on the color for the clouds beneath.
Any color is good.
It is your thought that I cherish.
Every item Your Majesty wears needs the utmost attention.
Just like Your Majesty said,
the sachet represents my thoughts,
and that's why I do not want it to have even the slightest flaw.
I like the light purple color of your dress.
It will also go well with the gold color of the dragon.
"The purple clouds come from the east."
"The gold dragon coils and rises."
Both are very auspicious omens.
When you are done with it,
I will keep it on me everyday,
and never let it get away from me.
Agreed?
Your Highness.
Is His Majesty staying at the Hall of Mental Cultivation
or with Lady An?
Is His Majesty staying at the Palace of Pearl Jade?
Yes.
Didn't you say that bitch has been turning His Majesty away?
Your Highness, that's just what I heard.
I don't know why she consented today.
Bitches always feign their feelings.
She distanced herself to entice His Majesty.
Your Highness, don't be mad.
It's not good for your health.
Your Highness, you added too much Pleasancy.
You're choking in the smoke.
Too much?
Why don't I smell any of it?
Why can't I smell it?
Yes,
His Majesty doesn't come and Pleasancy has lost its scent.
Concubine Sourire has recovered and been able to serve His Majesty.
This is a relief to my heart.
I thank Your Majesty.
Your Majesty, Consort Nian requests an audience.
Her Highness hopes to personally extend her regards.
It's cold outside. Ask her to return.
Greeting me in person isn't necessary.
Her Highness said she understands
that Your Majesty is not willing to see her,
So she asks only to come in and bow to Your Majesty distantly.
Let her in to bow to His Majesty.
It's almost the New Year.
Allowing her now will take this off her mind
and she won't have to come again.
Let her in.
Yes.
His Majesty summons Consort Nian.
I haven't greeted Your Majesty for a long time.
So I came to pay my respects to Your Majesty.
Rise.
I thank Your Majesty.
I dare not ask for Your Majesty's forgiveness.
I copied ten volumes of sutra during
the time I spent alone in my palace.
I sent them to the monks at the Baohua Hall today
so that they can chant and pray for Your Majesty.
I acknowledge that. You can go back now.
Yes.
Concubine Sourire has also come out.
What a lively room!
I bid Your Majesty goodbye.
It's too cold to write in the winter.
You should copy the sutras in the spring.
Yes.
I like the purple dress you were wearing yesterday.
You should order a few more dresses like that
from the Household Department.
I thank Your Majesty.
Sourire, you've finally come through the difficult time.
I was so worried about you.
It wasn't a difficult time.
We could have visited each other often
if you were concerned about me.
Isn't that so, Lady An?
You were in high favor when Concubine Sourire was ill.
How could you have time to
spend with your sisters of old times?
What were you looking at?
I was thinking that since it's almost the New Year,
Princess Wenyi will be so happy if
Your Majesty can spend more time with her.
Today, although His Majesty did not
grant forgiveness to Consort Nian,
he also did not punish her.
It's obvious that she still has the potential to regain favor.
I realized this after losing my child —
as long as Nian Gengyao and the Nian family stand,
His Majesty won't kill Nian Shilan no matter how big her mistakes are.
Military power surpasses sovereign power.
As the monarch, His Majesty has to exercise forbearance.
That, I don't quite understand.
But what happened between you and Lingrong today?
It seems to me that you two have drifted far apart.
Perople can drift away whether they visit each other or not.
It's not worthwhile if it's for His Majesty's favor.
I saw that she was yielding to you today.
Was that really necessary?
Lingrong ...
She's good at "retreating to advance".
People's hearts change like temperature
and they are only revealed over time.
It's not worthwhile to distance her for His Majesty.
But I'll leave it up to you if it's for something else.
The three of us entered the palace on the same day.
It's not easy, but we have come a long way together.
If she did something wrong,
we should be more forgiving while we can.
Meizhuang, I'm fortunate to have you
treating me just the same for decades.
The snow has stopped.
I shall pay my respects to the Empress Dowager.
Take care walking in the snow.
Jinxi, come walk with me in the imperial garden.
Jade, you can return now.
How nice seeing you both here!
I was just thinking that
this is such a rare view of the garden
as if it was decorated with crystals.
It would be such a shame if I am the only admirer.
May I invite you both to join me?
I was on my way to visit Wenyi.
But I'm obliged to accompany Your Highness as I haven't
seen Your Highness for a long time.
What about you, Lady Fuca?
I believe you won't refuse me.
Your Highness, I have agreed
to go to the theater with Consort Astuce.
I'm afraid it's not a good time.
It might not be a good time,
but it might be worse
if other people think that you're unwilling to see me
because you feel guilty about something.
Not at all.
Translators: The Magpie Bridge Brigade 鹊桥小队翻译组
https://magpiebridgebrigade.cn
Twitter/FB/IG @BrigadeMagpie 公众号/微博: 鹊桥小队翻译组
Theme: The Lonely Phoenix
[phoenix is the symbol of an empress]
I dimly recall the colorful blooms in every summer.
They are as distant as the autumn moon in the water.
He loved me with a volatile heart.
And before I knew it, we fell apart.
Behind me are the promises and longing.
Before me lie the flute and the zither.
I loved you with my body and soul
But you hurt me from head to toe.
My wish ran athwart
and I ended up a fool of my destiny.
My love was the wind-swept flowers from a tree.
A plum bloomed in winter hoping for a fruitful summer.
But the irresistible winds of destiny destroyed her wish.
You can hear the flapping of a phoenix
but you will never see it.
What you see is the falling leaves from the phoenix tree.
The falling leaves from the phoenix tree.